Guide to the Bettye Lane photographs, 1959-2007, bulk 1970s-1980s RL.00793
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Bettye Lane photographs
1959-2007, bulk 1970s-1980s
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Lane, Bettye
RL.00793
2.5 Linear Feet 947 items
Photojournalist who documented the women's movement and associated human rights issues since the 1960s. The photographs in the collection date from 1959 to 2007, with the bulk taken by Lane in the 1970s and 1980s. Subjects focus largely on events and individuals. Events include consciousness raising groups, planning meetings, and local women's conferences. Large events include Equal Rights Amendment demonstrations, and International Women's Year and National Organization for Women conferences and marches, in major cities such as New York City, Washington D.C., Mexico City, and Houston. Other events folders document Pro-Choice rallies and protests addressing harassment, sexism, and violence towards women. Another large series documents women involved in the movement, from feminist leaders to event attendees and coordinators. Subject folder photographs are of women at work, women athletes, men for women's rights, and events relating to daycare, feminist slogans and signs, lesbian rights, opposition, women of color, sexist images, and sexual health. Smaller sets of images document protests against war, pornography, and nuclear power. The collection also includes photographs of Bettye Lane and her original inventory sheets. Acquired as part of the Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture.
Arrangement
Arranged in three major series: Events, People, and Subjects.
Biographical Note for Bettye Lane
Chronology
1930 September 19 Born Elizabeth Foti, to an Italian immigrant family in Boston, Massachusetts
1959-1962 Attended Boston University School of Public Relations and Communications
1959-1962 Affiliated with Harvard University News Office
1960 Hired by CBS Television
1962-1964 Photojournalist with The Saturday Evening Post
1966-1977 Photojournalist for the Associated Press and the National Observer
1970 Covered the first Women's March for Equality in New York City, launching her involvement with the women's movement
1977-2000s Became a freelance photojournalist and was dubbed the official photographer of the women's movement; continued taking assignments from Time, Life, and the Associated Press Documented through her photography not only the women's movement, but also the gay rights and anti-war movements
2002 Contributed her work to a group exhibition entitled "'For Which it Stands': The American Flag in Social Protest" at the Smithsonian Institution in Washington D.C.
2012 Died September 19, aged 82, in New York City
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Bettye Lane photographs were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase in 2007.
Collection Overview
The Bettye Lane photographs date from 1959 to 2007, with the bulk taken in the 1970s and 1980s. Subjects focus largely on events and individuals. Events include consciousness raising groups, planning meetings, and local women's conferences. Large events include Equal Rights Amendment demonstrations, and International Women's Year and National Organization for Women conferences and marches, in major cities such as New York City, Washington D.C., Mexico City, and Houston. Other events folders document Pro-Choice rallies and protests addressing harassment, sexism, and violence towards women. Another large series documents women involved in the movement, from feminist leaders to event attendees and coordinators. Subject folder photographs are of women at work, women athletes, men for women's rights, and events relating to daycare, feminist slogans and signs, lesbian rights, opposition, women of color, sexist images, and sexual health. Smaller sets of images document protests against war, pornography, and nuclear power. The collection also includes a folder of photographs of Bettye Lane spanning her career.
The photographs are arranged into three series, Events, People, and Subjects, with subdivisions in alphabetical order, and the prints within in date or alphabetical order. The original order as assembled by Lane is for the most part intact, with folder titles deriving from the original headings. Included in each folder are her original annotated inventory sheets, which include dates, photo identification codes, and titles.
Almost all the prints are unmounted black-and-white gelatin silver process prints, with some color photographs scattered throughout, and a few digital prints from the 2000s. The larger prints all have detailed information on the backs, many giving names of individuals present, details on the events, and contextual notes. There are also a few photocopies scattered throughout. There are some duplicate images or cropped versions. The most typical sizes are 8x10 and 6 1/4 x 9 1/4 inches, with some snapshots found in a few folders.
There is some overlap with Bettye Lane images in other U.S. institutional collections, noted below, but many of the images at Duke University are unique.
Acquired as part of the Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture.
Related Material
Bettye Lane Photographs, 1969-1981 (1500 items)
Schlesinger Library, Radcliffe Institute
Bettye Lane papers, 1979-1980 [photographs], 0.2 linear ft. (21 items)
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution, Washington, D.C.
The International Gay Information Center Archives, Ephemera: Photographs, Bettye Lane Series
The New York Public Library, Humanities and Social Sciences Library, Manuscripts and Archives Division
Demonstrations -- United States -- Photographs; Documentary Photography -- United States; Equal rights amendments -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Feminism -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Feminists -- Photographs; Gay rights movement -- United States -- History -- 20th century; International Women's Year, 1975; Photojournalists -- United States; Pornography -- Political aspects -- United States; Pro-choice movement -- United States; Protest movements -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Protest movements -- United States -- Photographs; Radicalism -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Women athletes -- Photographs; Women employees -- Photographs; Women labor union members -- Photographs; Women's rights -- United States; Women -- United States -- Political activity -- History -- 20th century; United States -- Social conditions -- 20th century; Black-and-white photographs; Color photographs; Gelatin silver prints; News photographs; Lane, Bettye; Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture; National Organization for Women -- History
- Events, 1970-2006; 442 items
  Scope and Contents
  Folders contain a wide variety of entries related to women's movement conferences, meetings, and demonstrations, arranged in date order. Some of the events are represented by a single image, while others are extensively covered. Folder titles are taken from the original headings assigned by Lane.
  Each folder contains an original annotated inventory sheet listing image titles, dates, image id, and location, taken from the detailed information found on the backs of most photographs. In some cases, prints from original "miscellaneous" folders have been removed and added to appropriate events folders in this series.
  - Conferences: International Women's Year, United Nations and Mexico City, 1975 March and June-July; 17 items (Box 1)
    Delegates and speakers typically represented by one image include: Betty Friedan; Jo Hulett; Esther Urista; Wynta Boynes (CORE); Jacqui Ceballos (NOW); Germaine Greer; Flo Kennedy. Includes an image of Mexican women holding signs advocating for family planning.
  - Conferences: International Women's Year, Houston, 1977 November; 24 items (Box 1)
    Delegates and speakers typically represented by one image include: Roslyn Carter, Betty Freidan, Betty Ford, and Jean Stapleton. An image of the march to the conference shows leaders Billie Jean King, Susan B. Anthony Jr., Bella Abzug, and Betty Freidan, with torch bearers Sylvia Ortiz, Peggy Kokernot and Michele Cearcy.
  - Conferences: International Women's Year, pre-Nairobi meeting in New York City, 1985 May; 2 items (Box 1)
    Two versions, large and small, of same image of two unidentified women, one black, one white, on podium or panel.
  - Conferences: NOW national meeting, New York City, 1972 February; 11 items (Box 1)
    Photographs of the conference hall, speakers, and a bulletin board display of notices and items for sale. There are close-up images of Betty Friedan, Jeannette Rankin, Shirley Chisolm, and Jacqui Ceballos, and scenes of a paper-mache statue of Susan B. Anthony being carried by demonstrators and destroyed by police.
  - Conferences: NOW national meeting, Washington, D.C., 1973 February; 10 items (Box 1)
    Photographs of attendees, workshops, and brainstorming and caucus sessions. There are images of Eleanor (Ellie) Smeal, a group from the Black Feminists Organization, and images showing displays, slogans, buttons.
  - Conferences: NOW national meeting, Houston, Texas, 1974 May; 6 items (Box 1)
    Images chiefly are from the conference's "Minority Workshop" and show women of all races interacting. There is also a portrait of an attendee and an image of the conference hall with large "You can't stop NOW" sign on wall.
  - Conferences: NOW regional meeting, Atlantic City, New Jersey, 1974 September; 13 items (Box 1)
    Many of the photographs are of the conference march, showing signs and slogans. Other images of of attendees. There is a portrait of Karen De Crow, NOW president, dressed as Wonder Woman, with an unidentified child in the same outfit. There is one color photograph of the march.
  - Conferences: NOW national meeting, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, 1975 October; 19 items (Box 1)
    There are many images of the conference march, showing signs and slogans. Other images are of attendees in the conference hall. Single images are of speakers Karen De Crow and Betty Friedan; Bella Abzug, Karen De Crow, and Mary Ann Krupsak, in a group; Mary Collins Robeson (Chicago NOW, sued Sears); Mary Lynn Myers (South Dakota NOW, Charter member of Veteran Feminists of America) and her mother; and the parents of the late Karen Silkwood.
  - Non-Conference: NOW 10th birthday party; NOW protest in New York City, 1974, 1977; 4 items (Box 1)
    One image of NOW protest in front of New York Times building; protest sign reads "The Times is dragging its feet / Call me Ms". Three other images are all copies of same image of women with NOW birthday cake (one is a photocopy).
  - Conferences: Sexism and Sex Education in the Schools, 1972-1973; 7 items (Box 1)
    Arranged in date order. Location of conferences was New York City. Images focus on attendees, group discussions, and signs/posters. There are images of Jan Crawford, NOW Media Committee, and Lee Walker, NY NOW. Two images are of high school Sexuality Speakouts, and others are from high school conferences and meetings on sexuality and sexism in the schools.
  - Conferences and meetings, other, 1970-1974; 20 items (Box 1)
    Consists of a variety of topical entries, most of which are represented by a single photograph. Arranged in date order. Images in folder: consciousness raising group, Women's Center, NYC, 1970 (2); Trade Union Studies, Cornell Univ.; Older Women's Liberation (OWL) marriage workshop, 1972, Marymount College; Women Learn From Women workshop, Barnard (Columbia Univ.), 1973 (several, including group discussion of job market); marriage and divorce conference, 1973, with Eleanor Livingston, Eleanor Guggenheim, lesbian activists Sidney Abbott and Barbara Love, and Mimi Lobell; sexuality conference, with Betty Dodson; Statue of Liberty and MS boat party balloons; women's trade union meeting, 1974; conference on men for women's rights, with Warren Farrell speaking, 1974; flight attendants meeting, 1974 (3); women in film conference, 1974, with Phyllis Chesler, Molly Haskell, and Eleanor Perry. Two folders of materials were merged to bring together separated images from the same events; their original inventory sheets are in folder 1.
  - Conferences and meetings, other, 1975-1989; 27 items (Box 1)
    Consists of a variety of topical entries, most of which are represented by a single photograph. Arranged in date order. Images are of: Political Prisoners Conference, with Native American Yvonne Monroe speaking, 1975; Native American women's conference, NYC; More Media conference, with Redstocking members attending (several), 1975; rights of women in prison, with Flo Kennedy speaking, 1975; consciousness raising planning group at NYU, with Center's manifesto on wall behind attendee; Writer's Symposium sponsored by Feminist Forum, 1976; Woman of the Year Awards, with images of Pearl Bailey, Betty Ford, Barbara Walters, and Navajo Annie Winetka; meetings of men in support of women's rights and childcare; Women's Office Workers conferences, 1977 and 1980; school and drugs symposium for women; 10th anniversary of Ladies Home Journal sit-in, 1980; Spirituality and Women; Asian ILGWU women at Labor Day march, NYC, 1981; jobs workshop at YWCA, 1985; Commission on the Status of Women (several), 1985 and 1999 [1989?]; and Veteran Feminists of America, with Jacqui Ceballos, Flo Kennedy, and Phyllis Chesler, 1993.
    Two folders of materials were merged to bring together separated images from the same events; their original inventory sheets are in folder 1.
  - Demonstrations: Against violence, rape, harassment, genital mutilation, 1972-1979; 19 items (Box 2)
    Arranged in date order. Locations are in New York City. The photographs document protests and meetings against sexual harassment; rape; battered women; street harassment. Additional images are from the Take Back the Night movement.
  - Demonstrations: Against violence, rape, harassment, genital mutilation, 1980-1991; 13 items (Box 2)
    Arranged in date order. Locations are in New York City. Photographs document protests and meetings against sexual harassment; rape; battered women; street harassment. Additional images are from the Take Back the Night movement.
  - Demonstrations: Anti-nuclear, 1975-1982; 9 items (Box 2)
    Arranged in date order. Locations include Shoreham plant, Long Island; New York Stock Exchange; World Trade Center; and streets of New York City. Chiefly images of feminists marching against nuclear power, and the Sisters of Silkwood group at a NOW conference in Philadelphia.
  - Demonstrations: Anti-war, 1971-2006; 14 items (Box 2)
    Arranged in date order. Includes five original color prints. Locations include Washington D.C. and New York City. Images are of anti-draft protests, anti-Vietnam War and Iraq War protests, police arresting protesters. There are also some photographs of the group Grandmothers for Peace. Kate Millett appears at an anti-Iraq War rally.
  - Demonstrations: E.R.A. (Equal Rights Amendment), 1970-1983; 13 items (Box 2)
    Arranged in date order. Locations include: New York City (Statue of Liberty, NY Public Library steps) and Washington D.C. There are a few images from meetings, including one with panelists Noreen Connell, Erika Jong, Elizabeth Holtzman, and Brenda Feigen (Fasteau), Greenwich House, New York City, 1978.
  - Demonstrations: International Women's Year, New York City, 1974; 5 items (Box 2)
    Images were taken at Federal Plaza and Union Square and chiefly show crowds at march. One photograph shows speaker Bella Abzug.
  - Demonstrations: International Women's Year, New York City, 1977; 16 items (Box 2)
    Subjects focus on the great variety of coalitions and factions that attended these demonstrations, including racial and ethnic groups, women workers, artists, Girl Scouts, pro-choice groups, and ERA supporters; there are a great number of signs and slogans shown in the images.
  - Demonstrations: Pro-Choice, birth control, and abortion clinics, 1971-1973; 14 items (Box 2)
    Arranged in date order. Locations include: New York City (Governor Rockefeller's office, Union Square, and St. Patrick's Cathedral). Photographs document protests and other scenes related to pregnancy rights, legalized abortion, birth control rights, and the Pro-Choice movement. A march down 5th Avenue shows a woman in a coffin borne by marchers. There is one image taken inside the first abortion clinic in NYC, 1973.
  - Demonstrations: Pro-Choice, birth control, and abortion clinics, 1975-1983; 17 items (Box 2)
    Arranged in date order. Locations are almost all in New York City (St. Patrick's Cathedral, NYU Law School, NYC Pleace Church), with two images from Cherry Hill, New Jersey, 1982. Protests relate to pregnancy rights, birth control, pro-choice, and the Hyde Amendment. Several images are from an abortion clinic where an abortion is in process. There is also an image from a YWCA pregnancy workshop.
  - Demonstrations: Pro-Choice, birth control, and abortion clinics, 1985-1989; 20 items (Box 2)
    Arranged in date order. Locations are chiefly in New York City, including St. Patrick's Cathedral, Planned Parenthood clinics, and a phony abortion clinic. Protests relate to pregnancy rights; birth control and pro-choice; and the Roe v. Wade Amendment. There are several images from workshops. One march image shows women's health activists Bill Baird and Merle Hoffman behind banner. A 1989 image shows union women marching for pro-choice.
  - Demonstrations: Pro-Choice, and protests against abortion clinic murders, 1994-1995; 4 items (Box 2)
    Arranged in date order. Locations are in New York City. Protests relate to pro-choice; the murder of abortion provider Dr. John Britton in Florida; and the murder of two women in Massachusetts clinics.
  - Demonstrations: Women's March for Equality, 1970; 10 items (Box 2)
    Folder contains a variety of images taken by Lane at the first annual Women's March for Equality in New York City, 1970. Images chiefly show marchers and the multiplicity of contingents, causes, signs, and slogans. Locations include Battery Park, Union Square, and St. Patrick's Cathedral.
  - Demonstrations: Women's March for Equality, 1971; 10 items (Box 2)
    Folder contains a variety of images taken by Lane at the second annual Women's March for Equality in New York City, 1971. Photographs chiefly show marchers and the multiplicity of contingents, signs, and slogans.
  - Demonstrations: Women's March for Equality, 1972; 6 items (Box 2)
    Folder contains a variety of images taken by Lane at the third annual Women's March for Equality in New York City, 1972. The photographs chiefly show marchers and the multiplicity of contingents, causes, signs, and slogans. Includes images from meeting held before the march; one shows Susan Brownmiller speaking.
  - Demonstrations: Women's March for Equality, 1973-1980; 12 items (Box 2)
    Arranged in date order. Folder contains a variety of images from Women's Marches for Equality in New York City, chiefly of marchers and the multiplicity of contingents, causes, signs, and slogans. Locations include Battery Park, Union Square, and St. Patrick's Cathedral. Bella Abzug appears in a 1980 image. Two of the march photographs are in color.
  - Demonstrations: Miscellaneous, 1971-2006; 100 items 3 folders (Box 3)
    Consists of a wide variety of photographs taken at demonstrations, marches, and rallies, most of which are represented by one or two photographs. Arranged in alphabetical order by topical title. Locations are almost all in New York City and Washington D.C.
    Topics include: animal rights, artists against Museum of Modern Art; Bakke affirmative action decision; a building takeover; day care; environment; poverty; prostitution and pornography; prisoners rights; protests against companies such as Olivetti; and sexism in the media.
    When present in large enough numbers, prints representing other topics have been removed from this original "miscellaneous" group, and new folders created in the Demonstrations subseries: these include protests against war, nuclear power, and violence against women. The original inventory sheets have been annotated, copied, and added to those folders.
- People, 1970-2007; 159 items
  Images were typically taken by Bettye Lane at events where the individual was speaking or demonstrating. These women are considered leaders in the women's movement, and include authors, artists, journalists, politicians, religious leaders, and social scientists. Most names are represented by one or two photographs; individuals with many images include Bella Abzug, Betty Friedan, Flo Kennedy, and Gloria Steinem. Many photos of individuals also show other feminists with them.
  Within alphabetical folder groups, the prints are arranged in alphabetical order by last name and within in rough date order. The sole exception to the order is the first folder, which contains images of Bettye Lane, dated 1959-2007.
  This series was originally two separate groupings; the groups were merged to form one series and the original inventory sheets from both placed in the first folder.
  - Images of Bettye Lane, 1959-2007; 43 items (Box 3)
    Dates (1959-2007) represent the content of the photographs, which are modern copies, showing Betty Lane in various locations where she was on news assignment. There is also an image of her press credentials, 1974. The last photograph is in color.
  - Abzug, Bella, 1970-1995; 43 items (Box 3)
  - Alpert, Jane, 1975; 1 items (Box 3)
  - Anderson, Rev. Carol, 1977; 1 items (Box 3)
  - Artists, miscellaneous, 2003; 8 items (Box 3)
  - Angelou, Maya (with Coretta Scott King), 1977; 1 items (Box 3)
  - Atkinson, Ti Grace, 1972; 1 items (Box 3)
  - Baker, Ella, 1980; 1 items (Box 3)
  - Barrett, Rev. Ellen, 1977; 1 items (Box 3)
  - Berger, Dr. Judith, 1977; 1 items (Box 3)
  - Braithwaite, Yvonne, 1976; 1 items (Box 3)
  - Brown, Rita Mae, 1981; 1 items (Box 3)
  - Brownmiller, Susan, 1976; 1 items (Box 3)
  - Caldwell, Sarah, 1976; 1 items (Box 3)
  - Chesler, Phyllis, 1973; 1 items (Box 3)
  - Chicago, Judy, 1980; 1 items (Box 3)
    Pictured with her "Dinner Party" installation at the Brooklyn Museum of Art.
  - Chisholm, Shirley, 1972; 3 items (Box 3)
  - Costanza, Midge, 1977; 1 items (Box 3)
  - Dubic, Isolda, 1978; 1 items (Box 3)
    Suffragist, supporter of ERA movement in 1920.
  - Dworkin, Andrea, 1983; 1 items (Box 3)
  - Ferraro, Geraldine, 1981-1984; 2 items (Box 3)
  - Friedan, Betty, 1970-1999; 18 items (Box 3)
  - Greer, Germaine, 1975; 1 items (Box 4)
  - Height, Dorothy, 1979; 1 items (Box 4)
  - Hite, Shere, 1976-1981; 4 items (Box 4)
  - Huarte, Delores, 1975; 1 items (Box 4)
  - Jong, Erica, 1978; 1 items (Box 4)
  - Jordan, Barbara, 1977; 2 items (Box 4)
    Two versions of same image; one is cropped.
  - Kennedy, Florynce (Flo), 1974-1988; 13 items (Box 4)
  - King, Coretta Scott, 1977; 1 items (Box 4)
  - Kuhn, Maggie, 1979; 1 items (Box 4)
  - MacLaine, Shirley, 1973; 1 items (Box 4)
  - Mead, Margaret, 1977; 2 items (Box 4)
  - Millett, Kate, 1977; 1 items (Box 4)
  - Morgan, Robin, 1979; 1 items (Box 4)
  - Neel, Alice, 1981; 1 items (Box 4)
  - Nevelson, Louise, 1979; 1 items (Box 4)
  - "Old guard feminists", 1987; 1 items (Box 4)
  - Paul, Alice, 1975; 1 items (Box 4)
  - Rankin, Jeanette, 1972; 2 items (Box 4)
  - Rich, Adrienne, 1979; 1 items (Box 4)
  - Ride, Sally, 1988; 2 items (Box 4)
  - Shange, Ntozake, 1981; 1 items (Box 4)
  - Shulman, Alex Kate, 1979; 1 items (Box 4)
  - Smeal, Eleanor (Ellie), 1978; 1 items (Box 4)
  - Sontag, Susan, 1986; 1 items (Box 4)
  - Steinem Gloria, 1970-2001; 23 items (Box 4)
    Some photographs are in color; a few are snapshot sizes.
  - Veteran Feminists of America - group portrait, 1993; 1 items (Box 4)